Finding Aid for Center for the Education of Women (University of Michigan) Records, 1919-[ongoing]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Individual Staff Files 1919-1999
  - Carol Hollenshead
    - 1972-1998
      - Institute of Gerontology
        - Research Articles, Studies, and Presentations
          - Older Women in Ads (Examples and Data) 1972-1982 (Box 26)
          - Older Women: Issues for the 80s (American Association of University Women Speeches) 1981 (Box 26)
          - "Older Women: Issues for the 80s", Carol Hollenshead paper 1980 (Box 26)
          - "Older Women: Research Issues and Data Sources" (conference, Ann Arbor MI) April 8-10, 1984 (Box 26)
          - Older Women workshops 1976-1977 (Box 26)
          - "Our Future: Implications of an Aging Society", Michigan College and University Personnel Organization meeting May 10, 1984 (Box 26)
          - Parke Davis
            - "The Closing of the Washington Plant: Report to Respondents" 1983 (Box 26)
            - NRTA / AARP Final Report 1982 (Box 26)
              ("Older Workers, Retirement, and Social Supports")
            - NRTA / AARP Interim Reports and Presentations 1981-1982 (Box 26)
            - "A Plant Closing: Influences on Older Workers", Joyce Beckett and Carol Hollenshead 1982 (Box 26)
            - Retirement Planning Program Final Report 1981 (Box 26)
          - "Past 60: The Older Woman in Print and Film" 1977 (Box 26)
          - "Preparing for Retirement" (Interview with Carol Hollenshead by Pat Materka) 1977 (Box 26)
          - "Qualitative Research in Gerontology: Methodological Issues and Findings--The Older Workers of the Washington Plant: A Phenomenological Investigation" 1983 (Box 26)
            (Also see research papers on Parke Davis and research utilization)
          - Qualitative Research Seminars 1982 (Box 26)
          - Qualitative Research Seminars (Bibliography and coursepack material) 1982 (Box 26)
          - Research Utilization
            - "Making Research Relevant: From Research to Practice" (workshop) June 12-17, 1984 (Box 26)
            - "Research Utilization Workshop" (Binder) 1983 (Box 26)
            - Research Utilization Workshop (Planning and follow-up) 1982-1983 (Box 26)
            - Research Utilization Workshop 1984 (Box 27)
          - "Retirement Research: Gender Issues" (series) 1981-1982 (Box 27)
          - TIAA-CREF study and report 1981-1982 (Box 27)
          - White House Mini-Conference on Older Women, Des Moines IA October 9-10, 1980 (Box 27)
          - "Women and Aging", Financial Management for Women in Transition National In-Service Conference October 10-12, 1979 (Box 27)
          - "Women, Work, and Age: Policy Challenges" 1984-1985 (Box 27)
      - Michigan Initiative on Women's Health Executive Committee August 1992-August 1998, 5 folders (Box 27)
        (Also see the separate MIWH collection)
      - MSA Survey ("Students' Views of Gender and Climate Experiences at UM") 1989-1991 (Box 27)
      - NSF/CURIES/WISE Study of Engineering Student Experiences 1992-1994 (Box 27)
        (Includes disks)
      - NSF Proposal / "Gender-Inclusive Science, Engineering, and Mathematics" (Notes) undated (Box 27)
      - OVPR Business 1988-1989 (Box 27)
        (Research Partnership Program and Presidential Initiatives Fund Proposals)
      - OVPR--Dan Fox/Scientia Negotiations 1986-1988 (Box 27)
      - "Technology and Structural Unemployment: Retraining Displaced Adult Workers" (US Office of Technology Assessment Advisory Panel) 1983-1985 (Box 27)
  - Sue Kaufmann
    The files of Sue Kaufmann's files (Associate Director, 1994-present) consist largely of documents pertaining to her involvement with the revision of the university's sexual harassment policies, as well as with the efforts to train university units in preventing and handling cases of sexual harassment. Other notable topics include records from the Women's Initiative Group (WING), the university women's advocacy group in which she and other CEW staff members were key members.
    - 1980-1999
      - Advocacy Institute (Institute for Continuing Legal Education) 1994 (Box 27)
        (Also see Kaufmann's Sexual Harassment files)
      - Alumnae Council 1991 (Box 27)
      - Alumnae Letter 1991 (Box 27)
      - Center for African and African-American Studies (CAAS) 1991 (Box 27)
      - "Breaking the Glass Ceiling", Women of Color Career Conference 1992-1993, 2 folders (Box 27)
      - College and University Personnel Association Midwest Conference 1992 (Box 27)
      - College and University Personnel Association National Conference presentation ("Attracting and Retaining Faculty of Color and Women Faculty") 1992 (Box 27)
      - Commission for Women Coalition Evaluation 1991 (Box 27)
      - Domestic Violence Arrest Policy (UM Police) 1992-1993 (Box 28)
      - Louise Erdrich Visit 1992 (Box 28)
      - Family Medical Leave Act (FMLA)
        - Evolution of UM Policies and FAQs 1988-1993 (Box 28)
        - "Is Your Institution Family Friendly" (Presentation Handouts and Reports), 10/8/1993 (Box 28)
      - Fetal Risk Policy 1990 (Box 28)
      - Emma Henderson Visit 1990 (Box 28)
      - Illinois Institute of Technology ("High Heels in the Men's Room: Breaking the Glass Ceiling" Luncheon) 3/23/1993 (Box 28)
      - Marilyn Lake Visit 1991 (Box 28)
      - Newsletter August 1991 (Box 28)
      - Sexual Harassment Conferences Attended 1992 (Box 28)
      - Sexual Harassment Policy Revisions
        (Also see "Sexual Harassment Implementation Team" in topical files)
        - Brochure and Poster Revisions 1993-1994 (Box 28)
        - Civil Liberties Board 1993-1994 (Box 28)
        - Civil Liberties Board Proposed Brochure 1993 (Box 28)
        - Departmental Sexual Harassment Policies 1990-1991 (Box 28)
        - General 1989-1999, 4 folders (Box 28)
        - Grievance Handler Job Position undated (Box 28)
        - Group on Sexual Harassment Training 1992-1994 (Box 28)
        - Lawsuits 1993 (Box 28)
        - National Background 1980-1988 (Box 28)
        - Newspaper Coverage 1986-1995 (Box 28)
        - "Sexual Harassment 1996 Scholarly Definitions and Everyday Realities" (Videoconference), March 27th, 1996 (Box 28)
      - Sexual Harassment Presentations and Trainings by date
        - Miscellaneous 1983-1991 (Box 28)
        - Wayne State University 3/19/1984 (Box 28)
        - GLERL (Great Lakes Environmental Research Laboratory) 6/20/1991 (Box 28)
        - "Sexual Harassment in the Workplace" (CEW Workshop) 1/30/1992 (Box 28)
        - CEW Staff Training 1/30/1992 (Box 28)
        - Royal Oak UM Alumnae and Clawson YWCA 2/10/1992 (Box 28)
        - Chelsea High School 3/4/1992 (Box 28)
        - Rackham / CEW Symposium Presentation (part of "Graduate School From a Woman's Perspective") 3/7/1992 (Box 28)
        - "Chilly Climate in the Classroom" (Student Organization Development Center Women's Symposium Workshop) 3/28/1992 (Box 28)
        - "Sexual Harassment in the Workplace" (Ann Arbor Community Center) 4/21/1992 (Box 28)
        - Mallinckrodt Sensor Systems 7/13/1992 (Box 28)
        - UM Faculty Ombuds Workshop 3/3/1993 (Box 28)
        - "Discrimination and Harassment" (School of Business Administration Forum on Mentoring) 3/19/1993 (Box 28)
        - Ultrafast Optics 5/28/1993 (Box 28)
        - Designated Complaint Handlers' Training Handouts May-November 1993 (Box 28)
        - Sociology Department 4/20/1994 (Box 28)
        - Designated Complaint Receivers April-July 1994 (Box 28)
        - Executive Committees, Deans, and Chairs 5/11/1994 (Box 28)
        - Women and Community Organizing Class, 11/3/1994 (Box 29)
          (Presentation on history and tactics of sexual harassment advocacy at UM)
        - Faculty Engineering Women, 12/6/1994 (Box 29)
        - GEO Gender Workshop 1/28/1995 (Box 29)
      - Students Rights and Responsibilities 1992 (Box 29)
      - Women of Color Seminar 1992 (Box 29)
        (Includes Photographs)
      - Women Writing Culture 1991 (Box 29)
      - Women's Initiative Group (WING)
        - Curriculum Task Force Introductory Course Survey (Findings and Reports) 1990 (Box 29)
        - Curriculum Task Force Introductory Course Survey (Planning) 1988-1989 (Box 29)
        - Compensation Program 1988 (Box 29)
        - Coordinating Council Minutes 1988-1990, 2 folders (Box 29)
        - Meetings with Zaida Giraldo 1989-1990 (Box 29)
        - Miscellaneous 1986-1991, 5 folders (Box 29)
      - Judicial Advisor Search (Box 43)
        [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2022 ]
  - Jean Manis 1972-1995
    Jean Manis' papers, ca. 1975-1995, document her oversight of various CEW research projects. The largest set pertains to the Ford Foundation grants to research the relationships between women, their work and educational status, and their quality of life. Another significant set of Manis' files pertains to studies she conducted in the 1990s on the climate for women students at the university, specifically "Project on the Graduate Experience" and "Women in the Engineering Pipeline".
    - CEW Research Report ("An Analysis of Factors Affecting Choices of Majors in Science, Mathematics, and Engineering at the University of Michigan") 1989 (Box 29)
    - "Facilitating Psychosocial Transitions an Normal Adult Development: The Implication of Intervention with Returning Women Through In-Depth Research Studies and Counseling" (Golden and Wiersma) 1978 (Box 29)
    - Family Enrichment Program Proposal 1993 (Box 29)
      (also see 'Project on the Graduate Experience' Files)
    - Ford Grants and Projects
      - Proposals, Questionnaires, and Coding
        - Ford I
          - Proposal: "The Education/Employment Transition: An Adult Development Approach" undated (either 1976 or 1977) (Box 29)
          - Questionnaire October 1977 (Box 29)
          - 'Short Form' Drafts and Codes 1978, undated (Box 29)
          - 'Short form' final version and telephone script undated (Box 29)
          - Codebook 1978 (Box 29)
          - Recodes 1980 (Box 29)
        - Ford II
          - Proposal: "Status in One's Own Right: A Life-Course Perspective on Women, Work, and Well-Being" February 1980 (Box 29)
          - Alumni Records Office Sampling Requests April 1981 (Box 29)
          - Questionnaire
            - Section Drafts and Comments undated (Box 29)
            - Original Pre-Test Version 1981 (Box 29)
            - Final June 1981 (Box 29)
          - Codebook (earlier, partial version) undated (Box 29)
          - Codebook (final version) undated (ca 1981) (Box 29)
      - Publicity, Descriptions, and Reports
        - CEW Demographic Trends 1973, 1978-1982 (Box 29)
        - Descriptions of the CEW Research Program 1982-1983 (Box 29)
        - Descriptions of two Ford Studies 1983 (Box 29)
        - Ford I Publicity for use in Ford II Grant Proposal, ca 1980 (Box 29)
        - Ford I Report to Respondents August 1979 (Box 29)
        - Ford II Reporting undated (Box 29)
        - Ford Publicity 1978-1980 (Box 29)
        - Frohardt-Lane notes on the demographics of the Ford samples 1983 (Box 29)
        - Guidelines for Small Ford Project Research Seed Grants, ca 1977 (Box 29)
        - Lists of Research papers based on Ford proposals 1984, undated (Box 29)
        - Summary of Ford III Project undated (Box 29)
          (Katherine Frohardt-Lane study based on Ford II data)
      - Research Papers
        - "Careers and Career Attitudes: Age, Education, and Timing Effects", Jean Manis and Hazel Markus 1978 (Box 29)
          (Folder includes tables from 1980)
        - "Combining Professional Careers with Marriage and Parenthood: Preliminary Findings from a Survey of Recent Recipients of Graduate or Professional Degrees", Jean Manis 1982 (Box 29)
        - Notes for an article on the effects of marriage, career, children, schedules, etc. on employment, Jean Manis undated (Box 29)
        - "Professional Women Today: The Impact of Occupational Attainment on Marital Satisfaction and Division of Household Labor", Jean Manis 1983 (Box 30)
        - "Psychological Consequences of Multiple Social Roles" Pietromonaco, Manis, and Frohardt-Lane 1984 (Box 30)
        - "Reentry Women", Jean Campbell chapter draft 1985 (Box 30)
        - "Relationship of Employment to Self-Perception and Well-Being in Women: A Cognitive Analysis", Pietromonaco, Manis, and Marcus undated (Box 30)
        - "Relationships among Career Orientation, Employment Status, Self-Esteem, and Life Satisfaction of Women: An Analysis of Age Differences", Jean Manis 1982 (Box 30)
          (Also includes earlier versions of paper with other titles)
        - "Some Correlates of Self-Esteem, Personal Control, and Occupational Attainment: An Overview of Findings from CEW Surveys of Educated Women", Jean Manis, ca 1984 (Box 30)
        - "Women, Work, and Well-Being: An Examination of the Relationships Among Career Orientation, Employment Status, Self-Esteem, and Life Satisfaction", Jean Manis, circa 1980-1982 (Box 30)
          (Drafts and revisions leading up to and including "Relationships among Career Orientation, Employment Status, Self-Esteem, and Life Satisfaction of Women: An Analysis of Age Differences")
    - Ford Meeting of Centers for Research on Women, February 6th 1979 (Box 30)
    - [Katherine] Frohardt-Lane NIH Proposal ("Psychological Effects of A First Child") 1983 (Box 30)
    - Honors Program, circa 1978-1982 (Box 30)
    - Landman, Wortman, and Manis co-authored articles, circa 1988 (Box 30)
      ("Mental Undoing of Real Life Events: Incidence, Content, and Emotional Correlates", and "Regret: Incidence Content, and Emotional Correlates")
    - [Hazel] Markus Survey and Report ("Continuing Education for Women: Factors Influencing the Return to School and the School Experience") 1972, undated (Box 30)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Forwarded Information 1981-1983 (Box 30)
    - Miscellaneous Survey Proposals and Questionnaires, circa 1972-1978 (Box 30)
    - Non-Traditional Student Survey 1980 (Box 30)
    - Project on the Graduate Experience
      (also see 'Family Enrichment Program Proposal' file)
      - General
        - Miscellaneous Codes undated (Box 30)
        - Questionnaires (Business School and General) 1992, undated (Box 30)
        - Telephone Protocol 1991 (Box 30)
      - Analysis and Findings
        - Analysis by David T. Burkham undated (Box 30)
        - Business School Summarized Open-Ended Responses undated (Box 30)
        - Engineering Data Summaries undated (Box 30)
        - Engineering Summarized Open-Ended Responses undated (Box 30)
        - Rackham Summaries of Data and Open-Ended Responses 1992-1993, undated (Box 30)
        - Summaries to Questions on Campus Climate undated (Box 30)
      - Individual Responses to Open Ended Questions undated, circa 1991-1993
        - Question 111 (By Department) (Box 30)
        - Question 143 and Question 144 (Box 30)
        - Business School Question 81 (Box 30)
        - Business School Question 99 (Box 30)
        - Business School Question 104 (Box 30)
        - Business School Question 130 (Box 30)
          (Day Program)
        - Business School Question 130 (Box 31)
          (Evening Program)
        - Business School Question 131 (Box 31)
    - Rackham Data and Reports 1991 (Box 31)
    - Research Funding Proposal to Jane Likert 1992 (Box 31)
    - "Role of the Self in Competent Performance", Cross and Markus Paper 1991 (Box 31)
    - Stewart and Tangri Study
      - Grant Proposal ("Well Being at Midlife for Black and White Women") February 1991 (Box 31)
      - Miscellaneous 1992 (Box 31)
      - Questionnaires, ca 1992 (Box 31)
    - Undergraduate Math and Physics Majors Data undated (Box 31)
    - Women in the Engineering Pipeline
      (Also see WIS in topical files)
      - First Year Questionnaire 1991-1992 (Box 31)
      - Second Year Questionnaire 1992-1993 (Box 31)
      - Blank Questionnaires 1993-1995 (Box 31)
      - Codes for Questionnaires undated (Box 31)
      - Cohort II 1992-1994 (Box 31)
      - Cohort III 1994 (Box 31)
      - Data Collected by Hyun Joo undated (Box 31)
      - Engineering Curriculum Committee Survey 1993 (Box 31)
      - Pipeline Advisory Committee 1992 (Box 31)
      - Pipeline Draft Report 1995 (Box 31)
      - Pipeline Project Proposal 1993 (Box 31)
      - UM Project on the Undergraduate Experience in Science and Engineering undated (Box 31)
  - Hazel Markus 1971-1980
    The highlight of Hazel Markus' files (Researcher, circa 1970-1980) are the records of the 1970s CEW participant studies she conducted and supervised. These studies were the precursors to and models for the research studies that CEW undertook as part of the grants it received from the Ford Foundation. While not as in-depth as Jean Manis' Ford project files, many aspects of the earlier work are documented in Markus' files, including several years' codebooks for both the CEW participant intake forms and the CEW questionnaires, original, completed surveys filled out by participants, and data analysis.
    - Computing Allocation 1975-1976 (Box 31)
    - Counseling Records Committee 1971-1973 (Box 31)
    - Ford Study Codings 1978 (Box 31)
    - National Institute of Education (NIE) Proposal
      - Budget Drafts, ca 1979 (Box 31)
      - Complete final proposal 1979 (Box 31)
        ("Self-Schemas, Career Orientation, and Occupational Stereotypes as Determinants of the Selection and Development of Scientific Careers")
      - DRDA (Division of Research Development and Administration) Submission 1979 (Box 31)
      - Jean Manis Sections undated (Box 31)
      - Section Drafts, ca 1979 (Box 31)
      - Proposal Project Binder, ca 1972-1980 (Box 31)
    - Participant Information Form Correspondence 1976 (Box 31)
    - Participant Studies
      - 1975 CEW Participant Follow-Up Originals (Survey, Codebook, and Report), ca 1975-1976 (Box 31)
      - Coding and Codebooks
        - CEW Participant Study Codebook, circa 1978-1979 (Box 31)
        - CEW Participant Study Project Binder (Including 1975/1976 codebook), circa 1975-1979 (Box 31)
        - Coders' Handbook (For use with 1974 Participant Data), 1975 (Box 31)
        - "New Participant Coding Codebook" undated (Box 31)
        - Participant/Counselor Sheet Coding Instructions undated (Box 31)
        - Notes on Coding Procedures and Summaries of Open-Ended Responses 1976 (Box 31)
        - Notes on Response Rates and Summaries of Open-Ended Responses undated (Box 31)
      - Nancy Sippel
        - Job Information and Classification Appeal 1972-1974, undated (Box 31)
        - Notes and Suggestions for Coding Participant Data 1972-1974 (Box 31)
        - Reports and Data Analysis 1971-1974 (Box 31)
      - Returned Questionnaires by CEW Mailing Date 1976-1977, 31 folders (Box 32)
      - Returned Questionnaires Received After Deadline undated (Box 32)
    - Research Assistant Job Descriptions undated (Box 32)
    - Research Symposium on Returning Women (Papers and Abstracts) 1977 (Box 32)
    - Women's Lives Papers 1977, undated (Box 32)
      ("Work, Women and Well-Being: A Life-Course Perspective", "The Return to School", and "Continuing Education for Women: Factors Influencing the Return to School and the School Experience")
  - Dorothy McGuigan 1919-1980
    Program Associate Dorothy McGuigan was involved in the center's program publicity and publications. Notable topics in her files include records of CEW programs (especially lecture series, conferences, and workshops); the early years of the university's Women's Studies Program; and the status of minorities and women at the university, especially as pertaining to the levels of women on staff and enrolled as students. McGuigan's papers also include notes and correspondence pertaining to her book A Dangerous Experiment, on the history of women at the University of Michigan.
    - Admission of Adult Students 1972-1977 (Box 32)
    - Affirmative Action Clippings 1972-1973 (Box 32)
    - Alumnae Correspondence and Historical Information 1965-1975 (Box 32)
    - Alumnae Talk (on History of Women's Movement and Impact at UM) undated (Box 32)
    - Art Collection 1972-1973 (Box 32)
    - Barbour Gym Closing 1976 (Box 32)
    - Black Women (Conferences and Papers) 1975-1978 (Box 32)
      (Includes Perspectives on Black Women-1976 BWIT-1978 etc.)
    - Black Women (Data) 1963-1972 (Box 32)
    - [Jean] Campbell Honorary Degree Nomination 1971 (Box 32)
    - Commission on Women (Minutes and Clippings) 1971-1972 (Box 32)
      (also see various files under 'Commission for Women')
    - Commission on Women (Subcommittees and Task Forces) 1971 (Box 32)
    - Committee on the Status of Women in Graduate Education 1971-1978, 5 folders (Box 32)
      (Includes the report "The Higher, The Fewer", March 1974)
    - Conference Participant Biographies and Paper Abstracts 1969-1977 (Box 32)
    - Conference Publicity 1970-1975 (Box 32)
    - Conversations at the Center 1970-1971 (Box 32)
    - Correspondence (Box 33)
      - General 1963-1972, undated (Box 33)
      - Intra-Office 1970-1978 (Box 33)
      - Michigan Daily and New York Times features, 1975-1976 (Box 33)
      - UM History 1971-1973 (Box 33)
    - Counseling
      - CEW 1970-1978 (Box 33)
      - High School 1970 (Box 33)
      - Medical School 1970-1971 (Box 33)
    - A Dangerous Experiment, 1970-1974 (Box 33)
      (Also see Ruth Bordin files and topical photographs)
    - Data on Graduate Education at UM and in the US, ca 1970-1977 (Box 33)
    - Data on Minorities at UM and in the US, ca 1971-1976 (Box 33)
    - Dearborn Campus 1971 (Box 33)
    - Discussion Guides 1975 (Box 33)
    - "Diversity Without Design: Continuing Education at the University of Michigan" undated (Box 33)
    - Employment 1971-1975 (Box 33)
    - Enrollment Statistics 1970-1976 (Box 33)
    - Evening Program 1969-1977 (Box 33)
    - Faculty Women 1966-1976 (Box 33)
    - "Families, Women, and Mental Health: The Minority Experience" (Conference), March, 26th 1979 (Box 33)
    - Ford Foundation Grant Project 1976-1977 (Box 33)
    - Historical Material on 19th Century UM Alumnae 1919-1968 (Box 33)
      (Bulk dates 1935-1955)
    - International Women's Year--Draft of Book from Conference ("Women and Educational Change") 1975, undated (Box 33)
    - International Women's Year UM Committee 1975-1976, 2 folders (Box 33)
    - Library (CEW) 1971-1972 (Box 33)
    - LSA Admissions Committee 1973 (Box 33)
    - LSA Commission on Graduation Requirements
      - Binder 1970-1973, 2 folders (Box 33)
      - General 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 33)
      - Response to Report 1973-1974 (Box 33)
      - Subcommittee on Admissions 1973 (Box 33)
    - Michigan Women's Studies Association 1973 (Box 33)
    - Mortarboard Survey 1970 (Box 33)
    - NAWDAC [National Association of Women's Dean's, Administrator's and Counselors] CEW Pre-Conference Workshop 1978 (Box 33)
    - National Coalition for Research On Women's Education and Development 1972-1973 (Box 33)
      (Also see topical files under topical files 'National Council for Research on Women')
    - New Research on Women Conference, March 15th 1973 (Box 33)
    - New Research on Women II, March 19th 1975 (Box 33)
    - Anais Nin Lecture 1972-1973 (Box 33)
    - Gail Parker Lecture 1972 (Box 34)
    - Part-Time Employment and Education 1960-1976, undated (Box 34)
    - Personnel and Job Classifications 1970-1977 (Box 34)
    - "Problems of Women's Continuing Education" (aka "Current Research on Returning Women") March 1, 1977 (Box 34)
    - Programs 1967-1979 (Box 34)
    - Psychology 402: Women in Non-Traditional Occupations (Barbara Gutek) undated (Box 34)
    - Publicity 1970-1978 (Box 34)
    - Report on UM Women Conferences 1977-1978 (Box 34)
    - Research on Women at UM 1973-1979 (Box 34)